בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ח lamed chet and
it is a very central דף daf as we shall see about
discussions in the גמרא Gemara relating to obligations between Jews and non-Jews.
So get ready for that, that's coming up. We start with the
משנה Mishna on ל"ז עמוד ב. lamed zayin amud bet. Let's take
a look. שור שישראל שנגח שור של הקדש, Shor she-Yisrael she-nagach shor
shel hekdesh, if a שור shor of a layperson gored an ox
belonging to the בית המקדש, Beis hamikdash, ושל הקדש שנגח לשור של
הדיוט, v'shel hekdesh she-nagach l'shor shel hedyot, or the בית המקדש's Beis
hamikdash gored that of a layperson, which probably indicates that in any
way the opposite of הקדש hekdesh is הדיוט, hedyot, that the first
word should have been הדיוט, hedyot, which as you'll see by the
side note some switch the גירסא. girsa. Okay, so a layperson's ox
gores הקדש's hekdesh or הקדש hekdesh gores a layperson's, פטור, Patur, you're
exempt either way. You might think it's crazy, you know, הקדש hekdesh
should always be entitled to compensation, they get a privileged position in
these types of issues. Nevertheless, from a formal base on a פסוק,
pasuk, there's exemptions in both directions.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, the verse says, שור רעהו ולא שור של הקדש. Shor
re-eihu v'lo shor shel hekdesh. It says if an ox gores its,
the ox of its neighbor, its fellow's ox, you know, if the
ox of a person gores his fellow's ox, then it's only if
it's his fellow's ox. הקדש Hekdesh isn't your friend. You know what
they tell you in high school, your principal, he's your pal, whatever,
but it's not true about הקדש hekdesh and God. God isn't your
friend, okay? הקדש Hekdesh isn't your friend, so it's not your friend's
ox, and therefore it's not included in the פרשה, parsha, and there's
a total exemption in both directions.
What does the בית המקדש Beis hamikdash do with their dead ox?
I don't know. What do you mean? They sell it or whatever.
They sell it?
Yeah, sure. בית המקדש Beis hamikdash sells something and פודה את podeh
et and then the ox goes out to חולין chulin and whatever
money they get for it. And the oxen they have are not
necessarily קרבנות. korbanot. Somebody might have donated oxen, they might have it
as an investment, whatever the case might be. Right, exactly. Okay. So
anyway, okay. Now, שור שישראל, Shor she-Yisrael, that's the first part. Second
part: שור שישראל שנגח לשור של כנעני. Shor she-Yisrael she-nagach l'shor shel
kena'ani. Now the גירסא girsa here is not כנעני kena'ani but נכרי.
nochri. The standard word, everybody thinks that if, I love doing this
when I give a lecture on this topic: Okay, everybody, what's the
word in the גמרא Gemara for non-Jew? So everybody says עכו"ם. Akum.
So it says: No, actually that was the word that was put
in by the censors. The word in the גמרא Gemara for non-Jew
is either נכרי nochri or גוי. goy. נכרי Nochri is like from
the תורה, Torah, מכור לנכרי. m'chor l'nochri. גוי Goy is more, I
mean גויי הארץ, goyei ha'aretz, but anyway it's more a rabbinic term.
And it just means a foreigner, right? It's a very neutral type
of a term. The problem was was that there was all this
stuff in the גמרא Gemara that's negative attitudinally or halachically about non-Jews.
And in the Middle Ages when some Jews converted to Christianity and
they told the Church about all the stuff in the תלמוד Talmud
that spoke out against non-Jews, the Church got into the business of
beginning to either censor or burn the תלמוד. Talmud. So as to
preempt that, the Jews went through a process of self-censorship, and they
replaced every time it said the word נכרי nochri or גוי goy
in the גמרא, Gemara, or almost every time, any time it was
even slightly problematic, with the word עכו"ם, Akum, because עכו"ם Akum means
עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, ovdei kochavim u'mazalot, which means star worshippers, so that
the Jews could say to the Christians: This isn't referring to you,
it's referring to those pagan star worshippers. Of course the irony is
that some of them began to understand that the word עכו"ם Akum
referred to עובדי, ovdei, C for Jesus's name, and then ומרים. u'Miryam.
So anyway, so they didn't buy that it wasn't talking about them.
They reinterpreted that it דווקא davka was talking about them. But anyway,
that's why עכו"ם Akum became the standard term for non-Jew in the
גמרא. Gemara. However, you know that a גמרא Gemara is particularly problematic
if it is not using the word עכו"ם Akum but is using
another word like כנעני, kena'ani, a Canaanite, which means: Oh, these are
talking about these ancient
Canaanite nations that haven't existed for thousands of years, it was never,
ever relevant for anybody real in our lives in our history and
so on. So כנעני kena'ani is a signal that you're really dealing
with something problematic. Sometimes it even goes further and says כנעני אנס,
kena'ani anas, a violent Canaanite.
And later here when we're going to deal with the issue about
גזל גוי. gezel goy. No, it's all no, but it doesn't matter,
it's all been glossed. None of this was from the time of
the משנה. Mishna. This is all things that have been censored in
the time of the Middle Ages. If you look through ראשונים, Rishonim,
the ראשונים's Rishonim גירסא girsa still is נכרי nochri or גוי goy
with all this stuff. But the printed version since the time of
the Middle Ages, well it wasn't printed in the Middle Ages, anyway
was כנעני. kena'ani. There's even one גמרא Gemara that actually talks about
עמלקי Amaleki where the original גמרא Gemara was גוי goy or נכרי.
nochri. So you know you're in for a challenging גמרא Gemara from
this perspective when it uses the word כנעני. kena'ani. Okay, so the
original text
was: שור שישראל שנגח לשור של נכרי Shor she-Yisrael she-nagach l'shor shel
nochri was the original text. A שור shor of a Jew that
gores an ox of a non-Jew or of a Canaanite, פטור, Patur,
you're exempt, you don't pay damages. But the reverse, ושל כנעני v'shel
kena'ani or ושל נכרי v'shel nochri שנגח לשור של ישראל, she-nagach l'shor
shel Yisrael, if a non-Jew gores that of a Jew, בין תם
בין מועד משלם נזק שלם. bein tam bein mu'ad mishalem nezek shaleim.
Whether a תם tam or a habitual ox pays full damages. So
it,
well right, this assumes that he's living in Israel and that he's
subject to your court system and so on, okay? So here, the
fact that you're exempt wouldn't be so terrible, right? I mean, you
know, you're exempt by הקדש. hekdesh. It's exempt in both directions as
long as it's fair, okay? Could be it's a different rule as
long as it's parallel. But here it's very unfair. You pay nothing,
they pay full. It's unfair in two ways, also because they're paying
not by the normal rule of half and full, but always full.
So we will see that in the גמרא. Gemara. First we look
at הקדש hekdesh and then we're going to get onto the issue
of the non-Jew. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מתניתין
דלא כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא. matnitin de'lo k'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya. Our
משנה Mishnah that says הקדש hekdesh is totally, you're פטור patur both
ways with הקדש, hekdesh, is not like
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא. Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya. דתניא, de'tanya, taught in
a ברייתא: Beraita: שור של הדיוט שנגח שור של הקדש ושל הקדש
שנגח שור של הדיוט פטור, shor shel hedyot she'nagach shor shel hekdesh
ve'shel hekdesh she'nagach shor shel hedyot patur, you're exempt both ways, that's
what our
משנה Mishnah says. שנאמר שור רעהו ולא שור של הקדש, she'ne'emar shor
re'ehu ve'lo shor shel hekdesh, the ox of your friend and not
the ox of הקדש. hekdesh. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר שור של
הקדש שנגח שור של הדיוט פטור. Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer shor
shel hekdesh she'nagach shor shel hedyot patur. No, it always works in
favor of
הקדש. hekdesh. If הקדש hekdesh gores הדיוט, hedyot, הקדש hekdesh is
exempt. ושל הדיוט שנגח שור של הקדש בין תם בין מועד משלם
נזק שלם, ve'shel hedyot she'nagach shor shel hekdesh bein tam bein muad
meshalem nezek shalem, pays full, just like the משנה Mishnah says about
the non-Jew, so רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya is
saying about הקדש, hekdesh, it always works in favor of הקדש. hekdesh.
Okay. So גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי קסבר רבי שמעון? mai
kasavar Rabbi Shimon? Now, we get what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
holds. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds רעהו re'ehu just says when
you're not, when you're dealing with הקדש, hekdesh, there is no liability.
All the פרשה parsha of liability is when you're dealing with a
fellow layperson. When you're dealing with הקדש, hekdesh, there's none of this
liability. But how, what is the logical
consistency? Question we're going to ask when we get to the non-Jew
case as well, with רבי שמעון בן מנסיא. Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya.
How do you read, unless you say it's like a rabbinic ordinance,
but if you think it's biblical, what is the basis to say
no payment in one way, full payment in the other direction? מאי
קסבר רבי שמעון, mai kasavar Rabbi Shimon, what does רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon hold? אי רעהו דוקא, ei re'ehu davka, if the word רעהו
re'ehu is supposed to be interpreted in its limited technical sense, meaning
only a fellow layperson, not הקדש, hekdesh, אפילו של הדיוט שנגח של
הקדש ליפטר, afilu shel hedyot she'nagach shel hekdesh lishter, so then the
פטור patur should go in both directions, like the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says. ואי רעהו לאו דוקא, ve'ei re'ehu lav davka, if רעהו
re'ehu is not being precise, is not meant in a limited technical
sense—and by the way, that's worth pausing for a moment to say
something about that, because we are also very habituated, we are very,
you know, trained to believe that anytime a פסוק pasuk says אחיך,
achicha, רעך, re'echa, עמיתך, amitecha, it's coming to exclude, well normally we
think non-Jew, but also maybe coming to exclude הקדש, hekdesh, that's a
technical sense of that word. I would say that in the פשט
peshat of the פסוקים, pesukim, certainly the intra-biblical evidence is that the
only word that clearly, and not even always, but at least sometimes,
has a limited meaning is אחיך achicha for your brother. For example
it says לנכרי תשיך ולאחיך לא תשיך, lanachri tashich u'le'achicha lo tashich,
to the foreigner you can lend with interest, your brother you cannot
lend with interest. So it's very clear, at least in some פסוקים,
pesukim, that the word אחיך achicha is in contrast to the foreigner.
Okay?
איש עברי ish Ivri or עברייה, Ivriya, that's
אחיך העברי, achicha Ha'Ivri, exactly.
Why would he say העברי? Ha'Ivri?
I don't know, but still, okay, I don't know. Anyway, I didn't
say it always means that, but clearly there are times where אחיך
achicha means, if not
by default it means, clearly there are times that אחיך achicha means
and not the foreigner. But the word like רעך re'echa and עמיתך
amitecha could be very לאו דוקא lav davka generic. If you look
at some English translations, right, it says, let's see, כי יתן איש
מום בעמיתו. ki yitein ish mum be'amito.
So it says a lot of translations will say if one person
hits another. Right? עמיתו amito doesn't mean anything except the other guy.
Okay, another person. But the, or you know, or רעך, re'echa, okay,
literally it means your friend, but it could just be a way
of saying another person, right? So if one man's ox gores another
man's ox, another's ox. But so the words רעך re'echa and עמיתך
amitecha in the פשט peshat of the פסוקים, pesukim, I do not
think there's any evidence within the פסוקים pesukim itself that they ever
come to exclude somebody like outside of a particular inner circle. But
that is
certainly ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta l're'echa k'mocha includes everybody. Well exactly, ואהבת
לרעך כמוך, v'ahavta l're'echa k'mocha, love your fellow person as yourself. Okay?
So it's really an interesting question, but חז"ל Chazal certainly consistently read
רעך re'echa and עמיתך amitecha to mean those within your circle, meaning
your fellow Jews. But I do not
think that that is פשט peshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. Anyway, that
is what חז"ל Chazal generally interpret it to mean. So the fact
that the גמרא Gemara here raises the possibility that רעהו re'ehu is
לאו דוקא, lav davka, I think is interesting. It somehow acknowledges, yeah,
sometimes it's a word that's not meant in a technical sense to
exclude someone else. Nevertheless, it's not really conceding the point I just
made because it's still saying the default meaning is exclude. is exclusive,
but sometimes it's meant a little לאו דוקא lav davka? *lav davka*.
Okay, but I, as I said, I would argue that the default
meaning is not exclusive. That's a specific rabbinic interpretation of that meaning.
Yes.
Yeah,
so again, I don't know if, that's what I said, it's a
good point. I don't know if אחיך *achicha* always means an exclusive
sense as opposed to נכרי nochri *nochri*. I know that it sometimes
definitely means that, you know. But I don't think there's any evidence
that רעך *rei'acha* or עמיתך *amitecha* ever mean as opposed to somebody
more distant. But you're right, like that type of a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, especially in קדושים *Kedoshim*, there are a couple of פסוקים psukim
*psukim* that sort of have עמיתך *amitecha* and אחיך *achicha* and whatever
all sort of thrown in juxtaposition to one another. Okay, so let's
take a look. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says,
okay, if it's דוקא davka *davka*, fine, you should be exempt in
both directions. If it's לאו דוקא *lav davka*, then you should be
חייב chayav *chayav* in both directions. ואי רעהו לאו דוקא ve-ei re'ehu
lav davka, אפילו afilu דהקדש נמי כי נגח דהדיוט לחייב *ve'i rei'ehu
lav davka afilu dehekdesh nami ki nagach dehedyot lechayev*, even הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh* should have to pay when it gores הדיוט hedyot *hedyot*. וכי
תימא לעולם קסבר רעהו re'ehu דוקא *vechi teima le'olam kasavar rei'ehu davka*,
no, רעהו re'ehu, *rei'ehu* means in this technical limiting sense to exclude
הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. וניהו *uninehu*? So then why is הדיוט hedyot *hedyot*
liable when it gores הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*? דהדיוט כי נגח דהקדש היינו
טעמא דמחייב *dehedyot ki nagach dehekdesh hainu ta'ama demechayev*, when הדיוט *hedyot*
gores הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* here's why it's חייב chayav *chayav*, משום דקמייתי
ליה מקל וחומר *mishum dekamaiti lei mikal vachomer*, because you can just
use, you know, logic as an override. The דרשה drasha *drasha* says
everybody's exempt in both directions, but then the logic comes and that
would dictate at least some level of חיוב *chiyuv*. What's the logic?
Because the logic is,
מקל וחומר מהדיוט ומה הדיוט כי נגח דהדיוט חייב כי נגח דהקדש
לא כל שכן *mikal vachomer mehedyot uma hedyot ki nagach dehedyot chayav
ki nagach dehekdesh lo kol shekein*. So from the פסוקים pesukim? *psukim*,
the technical word of the פסוקים psukim. *psukim* gets everybody at zero.
Logic says okay, but at least מסברא *misvara* you've got to pay
if you gore הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. Fine, says the גמרא gemara *Gemara*,
דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון *dayo livo min hadin lihiyot kenadon*,
it's sufficient for what you learned out to be like the original
basis of the law. So מה להלן תם tam חצי נזק nezek,
*ma lehalan tam chatzi nezek*, so the same way if you're by
a הדיוט *hedyot* you pay half for the תם *tam* ox, הכא
נמי חצי נזק *hacha nami chatzi nezek*. So the basis of paying
הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* is the same basis of paying הדיוט *hedyot*. It
should follow the rule of half and full, not full the entire
time. So I get how you could get from the פסוקים pesukim
*psukim* הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* never pays you, that's רעהו re'ehu, *rei'ehu*, you
pay הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* the same way you would pay הדיוט *hedyot*.
That would be because of some type of a logic. Okay, but
I can't get how הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* doesn't pay you and you
pay הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* full. All right, so let's see what the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says. אלא אמר ריש לקיש *ela amar Reish Lakish*,
says ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, הכל היו בכלל נזק שלם *hakol hayu
bichlal nezek shaleim*. Originally, right now what you have to understand is
that the פסוקים pesukim *psukim* have the word רעהו re'ehu *rei'ehu* by
the תם *tam*. It says, right, כי
יגח שור איש את
שור רעהו ki
yigach shor ish et
shor re'ehu ומת ומכרו את השור החי וחצו את כספו *ki yigach
shor ish et shor rei'ehu
vamet
umachru et hashor hachai
vechatzy et kaspo*. That's our half, וחצו את כספו *vechatzy et kaspo*.
Okay, I know, we're not going to worry about that right now.
וגומר *ugomer*. Just those who say כל פסוק pasuk דלא פסקיה משה
*kol pasuk dela paskei Moshe*. Okay. או נודע כי שור נגח הוא
מתמול שלשום *o noda ki shor nagach hu mitmol shilshom*, כי שור
נגח *ki shor nagach*, right, הוא מתמול שלשום *hu mitmol shilshom*, so
this is תם *tam*, והועד בבעליו ולא ישמרנו *vehu'ad bive'alav velo yishmerenu*,
what is it? בהמה איש ish. או אשה *behema ish o isha*.
No, בהמה איש ish או אשה *behema ish o isha* is a
different one. או נודע כי שור נגח הוא מתמול שלשום והועד בבעליו
*o ki noda ki shor nagach hu mitmol shilshom vehu'ad bive'alav*. No,
that's the, that's the case of the כופר *kofer*. What's the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*? או כי נודע כי שור נגח *o ki noda ki
shor nagach*. Yeah,
והועד בבעליו שלם
ישלם שור תחת השור
והמת יהיה לו *vehu'ad
bive'alav shaleim yeshaleim shor tachat hashor vehamet yihyeh lo*.
What is it? או נודע כי שור נגח
הוא מתמול שלשום והועד
בבעליו ולא ישמרנו *o noda ki shor nagach hu
mitmol shilshom vehu'ad bive'alav velo yishmerenu*?
והמת *vehamet*? ובעליו *uva'alav*?
שלם
ישלם *shaleim yeshaleim*.
Okay, fine, שלם ישלם *shaleim yeshaleim*. Okay, so that's full. Okay, fine,
thank you. Okay, so let's see what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*'s answer
is. אמר ריש לקיש הכל היו בכלל נזק שלם *amar Reish Lakish
hakol hayu bichlal nezek shaleim*. Here it doesn't say רעהו re'ehu *rei'ehu*,
right? כי יגח שור איש ki yigach shor ish את שור רעהו
shor re'ehu. *ki yigach shor ish et shor rei'ehu*. Here it doesn't
say רעהו *rei'ehu*. It just says one ox gored another. So if
I only had this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, I would say whether הדיוט
*hedyot*, whether הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*, if I just started with this, my
default would be you're always going to pay full. Okay, if the
תורה Torah *Torah* had never written this פרשה parashah, *parsha*, it just
said this thing. Of course it says נגח הוא מתמול שלשום *nagach
hu mitmol shilshom*, but whatever, if I just had this פרשה parashah
*parsha* I would say you always pay full and you always pay
everyone full. There's no word of רעהו *rei'ehu*. So the default is
everybody pays everybody full. Okay, so הכל היו בכלל נזק שלם כשפרט
לך הכתוב רעהו גבי תם *hakol hayu bichlal nezek shaleim kesheparat lecha
hakatuv rei'ehu gabi tam*, when it went and pinned said רעהו *rei'ehu*
by תם *tam*, רעהו דתם משלם חצי נזק *rei'ehu detam meshaleim chatzi
nezek*, מכלל דהקדש בין תם בין מועד muad. משלם נזק שלם *michlal
dehekdesh bein tam bein mu'ad meshaleim nezek shaleim*. He says, ah, so
what this is saying is if you are your if normally you
pay full. If it happens to be that it's your neighbor's ox
and it's the first three times you're going to pay half. Okay,
meaning that הקדש, hekdesh which isn't your neighbor's ox, the first three
times will pay how much? Full. We start with the default of
full and then you work down to a half. So הקדש hekdesh.
remains full, only your רעהו is half. Okay, that explains how you
get from the פסוק pasuk that הקדש hekdesh, pays full, but we're
still left with the problem: then say the same thing when a
הדיוט goring when a when a when a so so if you're
goring הקדש, hekdesh. you pay full, right? Because only when you gore
a הדיוט do you pay half, when you gore הקדש hekdesh. you
pay full. So say the same in reverse. When הקדש hekdesh gores
you, it pays full, right? If this if we're starting this way,
we basically start by full, everyone, and then this says oh one
minute, if if you're goring your רעהו, you pay half. If you're
goring הקדש, hekdesh you're going to still pay full. So then say
when הקדש hekdesh, gores you, it still pays full. Okay, so the
גמרא gemara doesn't answer that. Let's just read the last line of
the גמרא Gemara, and I'll tell you what רשי rashi says. דאם
כן נכתוב קרא להאי רעהו גבי מועד. de-im ken niktov kra le-hai
re'ehu gabei muad. If it wanted to exclude paying at all, paying
full payment, it should have said by מועד. muad. Since it says
it by half, what it's really telling you is that everybody is
full and when you gore הקדש hekdesh and you only pay half
when you gore your friend's ox. When you gore הקדש's hekdesh ox,
you still pay full. Fine, but then still, why don't you say
that הקדש hekdesh. is going to pay full when it gores you?
So רשי rashi basically says, so רשי's rashi answer to that and
I have to remember if I can if I can recall רשי's
rashi answer, one minute.
הקדש hekdesh is goring you.
I don't know. I can't, hold on. הקדש hekdesh is goring you,
pays half.
You gore הקדש. hekdesh
Yeah, רשי rashi says like this. רשי rashi focuses on also the
word איש. ish Okay, so he says like this. He says in
the case of you goring הקדש, it's it's a שור איש, shor
ish, it's your ox, but it's not goring שור רעהו. shor re'ehu?
So it's your ox which gored something but not רעהו, so it
doesn't get to go half, it's going to have to be full.
Okay, that's how you read it. If you're your ox gores הקדש.
Okay, is כי יגח שור איש ki yigach shor ish. correct? Is
it your ox? Yes. Okay, did it gore שור רעהו? shor re'ehu,
No. So you're not going to get to pay half, you're going
to have to go back to pay full. That's why your ox
pays full by הקדש. Let's say it's הקדש's ox, okay? So כי
יגח שור איש. shor ish. One minute, is it הקדש's ox? No.
Is it an איש's ox? No. So it's הקדש, it's not an
איש's ox. So if it's not even begin, somehow the logic is
if it doesn't begin to be in this פרשה, then it all
starts then it all starts at zero. You have to like initially
get into here. Oh, you're in here, you don't pay half. If
you don't pay half, you're going to pay full. But הקדש doesn't
even get into the opening פרשה because it's not even שור איש.
That's somewhat of רשי's rashi answer. Anyway, we'll accept it and move
on. Okay, so somehow he's going to learn from the פסוק pasuk?
this imbalance, but it's obviously a big problem of this problem of
the lack of parallel. And now we're going to continue with this
with the non-Jew where the גמרא Gemara is going to significantly switch
tracks. Okay, I have to just say about this שור רעהו, I
can't not mention of course the famous אבן עזרא ibn ezra because
he quotes a קראי karai commentator who I forget who he quotes,
בן זוטא ben zuta or something like that, who says something like
כי יגח שור איש את שור רעהו means one ox gores its
fellow ox. So רעהו as the friend of the ox. So אבן
עזרא ibn ezra says אין לשור רע אלא בן זוטא בלבד. ein
le-shor rea ela ben zuta bilvad.
An ox has no has no friend except for this בן זוטא
ben zuta guy. So anyway, all right, but yeah. It's only testified
against its owner
or that's the phrase and it says that הקדש הועד בבעליו, huad
biv'alav, that you can't
right, which so it can't be הקדש.
Can't be הקדש because הקדש you can't testify against it. Right, and
that's how you can't move from תם
to מועד.
Yes,
that's correct. Okay, all right, so let's go on. So now the
גמרא Gemara. says like this. שור שלנו שנגח שור של כנעני או
של נכרי פטור. shor she-lanu she-nagach shor shel kena'ani o shel nokhri
patur. So now we're going to have the same problem and for
whatever reason even though we seem to have figured it out above
by הקדש at least according to ר' שמעון בן מנסיא, r' shimon
ben menashya, that we're going to still we're going to have once
again the same problem. Okay, אמרי ממנפשך, amri mimanaphshakh, look, make up
your
mind. אי רעהו דוקא, ei re'ehu davka, if רעהו means it דנכרי
כי נגח דישראל נמי לפטור, de-nokhri ki nagach de-yisrael nami liftor, so
then you should be exempt in both directions. ואי רעהו לאו דוקא,
if it doesn't have a technical meaning, אפילו דישראל כי נגח דכנעני
נחייב. afilu de-yisrael ki nagach de-kena'ani nechayev. Alright, thank you. אפילו ישראל
Yisrael דנגח denagach דכנעני de-Kena'ani נחייב. nechayev. So then be חייב in
both directions, okay? How are you פטור patur in one direction and
חייב in the other? Just like the הקדש'ס Hekdesh's question according to
רב שמעון בן מנסיא. Reb Shimon ben Menasya. אמר רב יוסף אמר
קרא. Amar Rav Yosef amar kra. רב Rav is trying to squeeze
it into the פסוקים pesukim which we maybe somehow managed to do
a minute ago. Here we're going to say a completely different take
on this. The פסוק pasuk. says עמד וימדד ארץ ראה ויתר גוים.
Amad vayimoded eretz ra'ah vayater goyim. God stood and he measured out
the land. He saw and he ויתר vayater somehow he permitted or
whatever we'll see what ויתר vayater means, the nations.
Yeah. שבע מצוות שקיבלו עליהם בני נח. Sheva mitzvot she-kiblu aleihem bnei
Noach. God looked and he וימדד ארץ, vayimoded eretz, he measured out
the land, he assessed people's observance of the מצוות, mitzvot, and he
assessed the seven מצוות mitzvot that the בני נח bnei Noach had
been commanded and that they had accepted upon themselves. כיוון שלא קיימו,
Keivan she-lo kiyemu, once God realized that they had not been living
up to their obligations, עמד והתיר ממונם לישראל. amad ve-hitir mamonam le-Yisrael.
So ויתר גוים vayater goyim means he made their property now free
to ישראל. Yisrael. God is fining, imposing a fine on the nations
of the land. Since you guys are not doing the בני נח,
bnei Noach, the מצוות בני נח, mitzvot bnei Noach, the Jews have
the right not to have to pay you when they damage.
It didn't go the other way around
when the Jews aren't keeping מצוות. mitzvot. Right, I know. Well, what
can I tell you? It's not a fair system. We get other
types of—we get 2000 years of oppression. Okay, so anyway, so this
is his explanation. Now, the in—the question here is, what does this
mean, התיר ממונם לישראל? hitir mamonam le-Yisrael? So does that mean that
we can steal from them? Or does that mean that, like in
these types of cases where it's a case of determining do you
have to pay damages and so on, the law can always operate
in favor of the Jews. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
עמד והתיר ממונם לישראל, amad ve-hitir mamonam le-Yisrael, תוספות Tosafot says משכח
דווקא בעניין זה שנגח שור שלנו שור שלהם, mashkach davka be-inyan zeh
she-nagach shor shelanu shor shelahem, or it could be שור שלהם לשור
שלנו, shor shelahem le-shor shelanu, either we don't have to pay them,
that's also a question. What's the התיר ממון? hitir mamon? That we
don't have to pay
them? That's where—or התיר ממונם hitir mamonam also allows a more active
thing, that we can make them pay up, okay, even though, you
know, pay us in full. But either way, it's still in the
context of—it's not straight stealing, right? It's basically in the context of
damages. It's being compensated for damages. So it's within that question of
paying or not paying for damages, there's more—you know, we can sort
of take, you know, make the law our advantage. אבל למאן דאמר
פרק הגוזל גזל עובד כוכבים, Aval le-man de-amar perek ha-Gozel gezel oved
kochavim, or נוכרי nochri I think it is, גזל נוכרי אסור. gezel
nochri assur. ניחא. Nicha. If your general position is you're not allowed
to steal from non-Jews, you understand. You understand why you need a
special פסוק pasuk, here and why the פסוק pasuk. has limited applicability.
It applies to these issues of allowing you to be compensated without
you being obligated to pay compensation. אבל למאן דאמר מותר קשיא. Aval
le-man de-amar mutar kashya. But if your position is in general that
you're allowed to steal from non-Jews, obviously a very difficult גמרא, Gemara
that's where it says כנעני וכנעני Kena'ani ve-Kena'ani and so on and
whatever, we're going to come up with that in about—in about 70
days, קיג, Kuf-Yud-Gimmel, whatever it is. I think anyway, then why do
you need this פסוק? pasuk? If you're allowed to steal, of course
you don't have to pay. You don't even need this פסוק. pasuk.
Okay. So, I mean, maybe it's a little different. Here you're doing
it within the courts; there it's a personal act or whatever. Anyway,
but certainly תוספות Tosafot is correct that the פשט pshat of this
סוגיא sugya is that nobody is giving license to outright theft. But
regarding this question of, can you demand compensation, are you obligated in
compensation, we have more latitude because of this principle of עמד והתיר
ממונם לישראל. amad ve-hitir mamonam le-Yisrael. Now the other question is, does
that עמד והתיר ממונם, amad ve-hitir mamonam, is the logic here that
it's a type of a
קנס? knas? God's punishing them and, you know what, we might as
well be the beneficiaries, okay? But basically, you know, they're just being
punished and that's sort of the logic behind it. Or is there
some deeper rational logic here? And what it's saying is, if you
understand that the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach are
basically, you know, Mendelssohn's way of thinking of the שבע מצוות בני
נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach was it was the Jewish idea of
natural law. But if you sort of think of it as some
like basic laws of morality and of society, then if—then the statement
that they're not doing the שבע מצוות sheva mitzvot is not just
a question about like they're not keeping שבת, Shabbos, so they're going
to get punished. You know, no, it basically is saying that they're
not participating in civilized society. If that was חז"ל'ס Chazal's view of
it, and we have to understand of course that those writing the
משנה Mishnah lived in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael under Roman rule and
under the oppressive, you know, Roman rule and so on. So if
their view is that they are not participants in civil society, then
you can understand a little bit more why it's saying that like
we have to just protect our own interests whenever interacting with them
and therefore, you know, we're going to take compensation and not pay
compensation. They don't actually, you know, you know, they're always oppressing and
stealing and doing whatever from each other and from us. So that
also maybe helps understand a little bit what that's about. Okay, so
for example if you look back on לז עמוד ב, lamed-zayin amud
bet, this seems to be what informed the רמב"ם'ס Rambam's explanation of
this in פירוש המשניות. Peirush ha-Mishnayot. If you look at the bottom
lower right-hand corner of לז עמוד ב, lamed-zayin amud bet,
you know, obviously this גמרא Gemara is very difficult and it's not
enough just to have the word כנעני Kena'ani in it, so there
are a lot of these side
margins. So if you look at this note here in the lower
right, it says like this: כתב הרמב"ם בהלכות נזקי ממון פרק ח'
הלכה ה', Kasav HaRambam Behalachos Nizkei Mamon Perek Chet Halacha Hei, לפי
שאין... Lefi she'ein... do you have this where it says a little
א Alef in brackets? I don't know what it says in yours,
mine's just a little note here in the lower right. כתב הרמב"ם.
Kasav HaRambam. Okay, you don't have that? Anyway, פרק נזקי ממון, Perek
Nizkei Mamon, לפי שאין הכנענים Lefi she'ein haC'na'anim or whatever, גויים, Goyim,
מחייבין את האדם על בהמתו שהזיקה, Mechayvin es ha'adam al behemto shehizika,
הרי אנו דנים
עמהם
כדיניהם, Harei anu danim imahem kedineihem, והוא מירושלמי. Vehu miYerushalmi. Yeah look,
they don't make people pay when they do damage, so why should
we pay them when we damage them?
כנעני C'na'ani damaged another כנעני? C'na'ani?
It's not כנעני, C'na'ani, it's גויים. Goyim. It's not כנעני. C'na'ani. Yeah,
but that's the argument. That's why we don't have to pay them.
Full damage? Yeah, exactly. Now how about the next one? How about
the full damages? So you look at the next statement. כתב הרמב"ם
שם, Kasav HaRambam sham, קנסו לגויים, Knasu laGoyim, not לכנענים, laC'na'anim, whatever,
לפי שאינם זהירים במצוות ואינם מסלקים הנזק. Lefi she'einam zehirim bemitzvot ve'einam
mesalkim hanazek.
So he doesn't say זהירים במצוות, Zehirim bemitzvot, he doesn't just say
סתם. Stam. It means that they're they eat אבר מן החי. Ever
min hachai. That's the שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva mitzvot B'nei Noach.
No, it means that they're not participating in civil society, they themselves
are not careful about preventing the animals from going around and damaging.
So therefore we have a right to take full compensation. So it
seems that I think what the רמב"ם Rambam is doing is reading
that into understanding into what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu is saying here.
It's not just סתם, Stam, look, they're not doing אבר מן החי,
Ever min hachai, we can take their money. It's that they're not
participating in civil society and in protecting people from being damaged and
so on, and therefore that gives us more latitude in these types
of rules. Okay, so that's I think a different way of understanding
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. There was some question out here before, no?
Okay, yes, but?
I mean, do the ראשונים Rishonim then come and say but however
לדרכי שלום Ledarkhei shalom you should pay them?
Yeah, I mean, not all the ראשונים, Rishonim, but whatever, but there's
a development of the הלכה Halacha that this gap gets closed definitely
by some, not all, but by some later פוסקים. Poskim. Okay, okay,
let's take a look.
By the way, if you want to see again how this
gets qualified because of the harshness of the statement, now on back
to ל"ח. Lamed Chet. If you look at the lower left corner
in the שיטה מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzet, it says the following:
ראה שבע מצות, Ra'ah sheva mitzvos, משמע דכל שמקיימים שבע מצות, mashma
dechol shemekaymim sheva mitzvos, דינם אצלנו כדיננו אצלם. dinam etzlenu kedinenu etzlam.
Ah, but if they're good, law-abiding citizens, we wouldn't have these differences.
ומעתה אין צריך לומר באומות הגדורות בדרכי דתות ונימוסים, Ume'atah ein tzarich
lomar be'umot hagedurot bedarkhei datot venimusim, quoting the מאירי. Meiri. So therefore
nations that actually are law-abiding and have religiously constrained with ethical laws
and so on, then these differences would not apply. And what?
Did he take from common what?
I don't know if he I don't know exactly, but let's I
don't know. But the point is we would not have this obvious
injustice. Okay, and if you want to look at the next one,
ממונם לישראל, Mamonam l'Yisrael, כלומר שראה שהאכזריים ולב רע להם. kolomar ra'ah
she'achzarim velev ra lahem. We're looking at the
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet now, ב'. Bet. ראה כלומר
שראה שהאכזריים ולב רע להם, Ra'ah kolomar she'achzarim velev ra lahem, והחשודים
על כל שאינם מצווים משבע מצוות, vehachashudim al kol she'einam mitzuvim misheva
mitzvot, וכל שכן שאינם מצירים בצרת אחיהם. vechol sheken she'einam metzarim betzarat
acheihem. Again, translating it not just as oh they don't keep מצוות,
mitzvot, but they don't care about damages that other people suffer, they're
completely disregarding of people's safety and their protection of their money. לפיכך
קנסם הכתוב כדי שישמרו שורותיהם, Lefikach knasam hakatuv kedei sheyishmeru shoroteihem, וכל
זה לא דיברו אלא על שבע אומות, vechol zeh lo dibru ela
al sheva umot, דכתיב לא תחיה כל נשמה. dechativ lo techayeh kol
neshamah. So the שבע אומות sheva umot is clearly a way of
distancing it, those other nations. But again, what's significant to us is
two things: on the one hand, you can see here an impetus
in terms of trying to protect from criticism and anger
from the Christians or the non-Jews who would read this and know
about this, maybe an own sense of self-awareness of the difficulty, the
discomfort about these types of distinctions. But I think interestingly, there is
an attempt, and I think that that might actually be what is
at the root of רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, to say this is
not just arbitrary. Oh yeah, they're רשעים, resha'im, we can just take
advantage of them, they don't do מצוות. mitzvot. It's specifically to explain
that they're not doing מצוות mitzvot has to do with them not
participating in civilized society, them being a danger to us and to
our money, them not caring about these types of laws and so
on, which actually can give some rational justification for saying that we
don't have to pay them, but we can demand full compensation. So
it's a much more lot... an attempt to make a much more
rational connection rather than just a broad justification to take advantage of
them. Yes.
It's interesting that the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet is kind of pegging
his interpretation on the censored version of the text, right? Because כנענים
C'na'anim means שבע מצוות sheva mitzvot means the שבע אומות. sheva umot.
No, no, no. He did not have the... he did not have
what you're... see here is a not a gloss of the text,
but an early attempt to
contextualize. He did not have the word כנעני. Kena'ani. He had the
word נכרים. Nochrim. No, he didn't. He had the word נכרים. Nochrim.
But what he's saying is,
but he's quoting רבנו יהונתן. Rabbeinu Yehonasan. רבנו יהונתן מלוניל Rabbeinu Yehonasan
mi-Lunel is like Trouillet, like 12th century or something. But what you're
seeing is the same move, you know, is a desire to say
this is too deeply either problematic in what others will say or
too deeply morally problematic, so we have to say it doesn't mean,
you know, normal non-Jews. It means a special type of non-Jew. What
then happened was that then actually got found its way into a
gloss in the text itself. Okay. All right, so we're having fun.
I told you it was a fun דף daf today. Okay, back
to the גמרא. Gemara תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi we taught,
I'm sorry, רבי יוחנן אמר מהכי. Rabbi Yochanan amar mehachi. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says from the following verse. Interesting by the way that
both רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan were אמוראים
Amoraim living in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael consistently
had it worse from their non-Jewish government than in בבל. Bavel. רבי
יוחנן אמר מהכי Rabbi Yochanan amar mehachi from the following verse. הופיע
מהר פארן. Hofia me-Har Paran. From פארן Paran He appeared, ממונם לישראל.
mamonam l'Yisrael. God revealed Himself at הר פארן. Har Paran. At הר
פארן Har Paran He made their money permissible to Israel. So this
might be a slightly different point because if this is referring to
the giving of the תורה Torah, at הר סיני, Har Sinai, it
might be a way of saying that if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, מפארן כשסיבב והחזיר התורה על כל אומות ולא קיבלוה. mi-Paran k'she-seiveiv
v'hechezir ha-Torah al kol umos v'lo kibulah.
That they didn't accept the תורה, Torah, you know, the famous thing
about God says to
בני עשו, Bnei Eisav, what's in it? No murder. No, we can't
take it. What's in it? No stealing. We can't take it. But
that's a little different. I mean, on the one hand, they're not
accepting the תורה, Torah? doesn't mean they're violating their מצוות. mitzvos. It
just means that they're not accepting more מצוות, mitzvos, right? But nevertheless,
if the גמרא Gemara means to be plugging into that מדרש, Midrash,
why are they not accepting the תורה? Torah Not because they say
we can't keep שבת, Shabbos, we can't keep כלאים. kilayim. Because they're
saying we can't keep the איסור issur of stealing and murder and
so on. So it's the same point. You know, it's not that
they're violating the מצוות mitzvos they were given, but it sort of
is demonstrating this violent, anti-social nature that, you know, through this, through
the eyes of חז"ל. Chazal. Okay, so that seems to be sort
of the common denominator here. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, שור של נכרי
שנגח שור של ישראל בין תם בין מועד משלם נזק שלם, shor
shel nochri shenagach shor shel Yisrael bein tam bein muad meshalem nezek
shalem, שנאמר עמד וימודד ארץ ראה ויתר גוים, shene'emar amad v'yimoded eretz
ra'ah v'yater goyim, ואמר והופיע מהר פארן. v'omar v'hofia me-Har Paran. Okay,
מאי ואמר? Mai v'omar? Why do you need two פסוקים? You got
it from the first one. וכי תימא האי עמד וימודד ארץ, V'chi
teima hai amad v'yimoded eretz, that thing about measuring out the land,
מיבעי ליה לכדרב מתנה ולכדרב יוסף, mibaei leh l'chide-Rav Masna u'l'chide-Rav Yosef,
you need it to teach you a different teaching, רב מתנה Rav
Masna and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So if you don't like that
פסוק, pasuk I'll give you another פסוק. pasuk, תא שמע הופיע מהר
פארן. Ta shema hofia me-Har Paran. מפארן הופיע ממונם לישראל. mi-Paran hofia
mamonam l'Yisrael. From פארן Paran God had made their money permissible to
Israel. מאי דרב מתנה? Mai de-Rav Masna? What are these other things,
ways of reading the פסוק? דאמר רב מתנה עמד וימודד ארץ ראה
ויתר גוים, de-amar Rav Masna amad v'yimoded eretz ra'ah v'yater goyim, מה
ראה? mah ra'ah? What did God see? ראה שבע מצות שנצטוו עליהן
בני נח, ra'ah sheva mitzvos shenitzvu aleihen Bnei Noach, He saw the
seven מצוות mitzvos they were commanded, ולא קיימום, v'lo kiyemum, and they
weren't fulfilling them, עמד והגלה אותם מעל אדמתם. amad v'higlah osam me-al
admasam. He didn't make their money permissible to Israel, He exiled them.
The same way He exiled us, the same way the תורה Torah
says that if we sin we're going to be exiled, when they
sinned they were exiled. Okay, ומאי משמע? u'mai mashma? So it has
no relevance to these הלכות. halachos.
It's פשט pshat in the תורה Torah itself.
Right, דהאי ויתר לישנא דאגלותי הוא. de-hai v'yater lishna d'aglusei hu. Where
do you see ויתר v'yater means sent them into exile? כתיב הכא
ויתר גוים וכתיב התם לנתר בהן על הארץ, ksiv hacha v'yater goyim
u-ksiv hasam l'nater bahen al ha-aretz, by the grasshoppers to jump on
the land, so you're moving, you're jumping on the land, you're moving
from one place to another. ומתרגם לקפצא בהון על ארעא, u'metargem l'kaftza
behon al ar'a, to jump on the land. That's one way of
reading, a different way of reading the פסוק. מאי דרב יוסף? Mai
de-Rav Yosef? What's רב יוסף Rav Yosef see? דאמר רב יוסף עמד
וימודד ארץ ראה ויתר וכו', de-amar Rav Yosef amad v'yimoded eretz ra'ah
v'yater v'chu', מה ראה? mah ra'ah? What did God see? ראה שבע
מצות שקיבלו עליהם בני נח, ra'ah sheva mitzvos shekiblu aleihem Bnei Noach,
He saw the seven מצוות mitzvos they accepted upon themselves, ולא קיימום,
v'lo kiyemum, and they
were not fulfilling them, עמד והתירם להם. amad v'hitiram lahem. He said,
fine, you don't want to keep it? Forget it. You don't have
to keep it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara. says אישתרי אישתרא? ishtari
ishtra? What, like, you know, I there's no good way of translating
אישתרי אישתרא, ishtari ishtra, but anyway, says, are you crazy? No, I
don't know how they translate that. But like, you know, the opposite
makes sense, אם כן מצינו חוטא נשכר, im kein matzinu chotei niskar,
the sinner is rewarded! Oh, you're sinning so much, forget it, we're
not, you're not going to be bound by it anymore. אמר מר
בריה דרב אבינא, Amar Mar brei de-Rav Avina, no, here's what it
means, לומר שאפילו מקיימים אותם אין מקבלים עליהם שכר. lomar she-afilu mekayemim
osam ein mekablim aleihem sachar. It doesn't mean you're not going to
be held accountable, you're not going to be punished. It means the
opposite. Even if you choose to do it, you're not going to
receive reward. Okay. And if you don't do it you'll be punished.
But now that you have shown such complete categorical disregard in a
way of thinking about, you sort of see yourself as אינו מצווה
ועושה, eino mitzuveh v'oseh, which is where the גמרא's Gemara. going to
go. You don't see yourself as being obligated anymore. You have such
complete categorical disregard. So even when you're doing it, you're just doing
it by chance, right? You're not doing it out of a sense
of commandedness. So therefore even when you do it you don't get
rewarded because you're no longer seeing yourself as commanded. When you violate
you're still going to get punished, but when you do it you're
not going to get rewarded. Okay. ומאי ויתר? U'mai v'yater?
How do you read the פסוק then?
What? He was התיר, hitir, he made it, he released them from
it, but yeah, not released them from the restrictions, he released them
from
the.
What's bothered about that is though, but you're still getting a civil
society that way. They're doing what they're supposed to be doing.
No, I mean even if by chance they're doing it, they're not
getting reward. That seems to be the point, right? That's why fundamentally
they're not doing it. So if it happens that they did it,
they're not going to get rewarded. Okay. What?
And they're not going to start doing it now if they're not
getting their reward.
Right. Exactly. Well, that's a good point. That's also still, right, they're
not a חוטא נשכר, choteh niskar, but it's not helpful to get
them back on the right track. That's a good point too. ולו?
v'lo? Do they really not get reward? והתניא—we v'hatanya taught in a
ברייתא—רבי מאיר אומר: מניין שאפילו נכרי—finally minayin she'afilu nochri it says נכרי
nochri, because we're about to say something good. Okay. מניין שאפילו נכרי
ועוסק בתורה—how minayin she'afilu nochri v'osek baTorah do you know even a
נכרי, a foreigner, right, who does the מצוות mitzvot of the Torah?
Now there's some later question about עוסק בתורה. osek baTorah. The גמרא
Gemara. seems to interpret as like לעסוק בדברי תורה—it la'asok b'divrei Torah
means learns Torah. But in this context and in all the פשט
pshat in the Tannaitic sources, עוסק בתורה osek baTorah only means does
the מצוות mitzvot of the Torah. So that's clearly the original meaning
and that's clearly at least the first meaning in this context, so
we're talking about doing מצוות, mitzvot, we're not talking about learning Torah.
מניין שאפילו
נכרי ועוסק בתורה הרי הוא ככהן גדול—gets minayin she'afilu nochri v'osek baTorah
harei hu k'kohen gadol rewarded like a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. ועוסק
בתורה שהוא ככהן גדול, v'osek baTorah shehu k'kohen gadol, תלמוד לומר: talmud
lomar: אשר יעשה אותם—again, asher ya'aseh otam we're talking about doing the
מצוות, mitzvot,
right, not learning—אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם. asher ya'aseh otam ha'adam
v'chai bahem. כהנים ולויים וישראלים לא נאמר—it kohanim u'leviyim v'yisraelim lo ne'emar
doesn't say כהן, kohen, לוי, Levi, and ישראל Yisrael would do the
מצוות—אלא האדם—any human that does it. הא
למדת שאפילו נכרי
ועוסק בתורה הרי הוא ככהן גדול—anybody, ha lamadeta she'afilu nochri v'osek baTorah
harei hu k'kohen gadol
even a non-Jew who does Torah is—gets as much reward as a
כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Ah, so you see that they are rewarded
for the מצוות mitzvot they do? And anyway, by the way, that's
even more. That sounds like they're even rewarded for doing our מצוות,
mitzvot which leads to a really fascinating question. There's a רמב"ם Rambam
that says that a non-Jew who does any מצווה mitzvah from the
Torah gets rewarded like an אינו מצווה ועושה. aino metzuveh v'oseh. And
the רמב"ם Rambam applies it even to a מצווה mitzvah like—are you
ready for this?—ברית מילה. bris milah. You think ברית מילה bris milah
is only meaningful for ישראל. Yisrael. Anyway, and so any מצווה mitzvah
you get rewarded, okay?
So they do actually get rewarded too?
Apparently. Okay. So that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying. So
how can you say they're not rewarded? So it says, אמרי אין
מקבלים עליהם שכר מצווה כמצווה ועושה אלא כמי שאינו מצווה ועושה. amri
ein mikablim aleihem sechar mitzvah k'metzuveh v'oseh ela k'mi she'aino metzuveh v'oseh.
This is sort of what I was already anticipating in my earlier
statement. They, yes, they get reward, but they don't get reward as
if they were commanded in doing. Now, not only does that apply
to the מצוות mitzvot, of תרי"ג מצוות taryag mitzvot of ישראל, Yisrael,
there they really are אינו מצווה ועושה, aino metzuveh v'oseh, okay? But
what it's saying is even the שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot
bnei Noach, because you're no longer seeing yourself as commanded, because you've
basically, you've categorically rejected it, even when you're doing it, you're doing
it not out of a sense of commandedness, and you will not
be rewarded as מצווה ועושה. metzuveh v'oseh. You'll be rewarded at the
level of אינו מצווה ועושה. aino metzuveh v'oseh. דאמר רבי חנינא—if d'amar
Rabbi Chanina you don't keep it, you're going to get punished. גדול
מצווה ועושה יותר ממי שאינו מצווה ועושה. gadol metzuveh v'oseh yoter m'mi
she'aino metzuveh v'oseh. It's greater to have a sense of commandedness and
that's your obligation rather than out of volitional. Now, two comments as
this is a very rich גמרא. Gemara. Two comments I want to
make. Number one is the גוי ועוסק בתורה, goy v'osek baTorah, okay?
תוספות Tosafot understands it means תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, which is not
פשט pshat of this גמרא. gemara But if you look at תוספות
הרי הוא ככהן גדול, Tosafot harei hu k'kohen gadol, he says הא
דנקט ככהן גדול, ha d'nakat k'kohen gadol, he says משום דדרשינן בסוטה
יקרה היא מפנינים—and mishum d'darshinan b'Sotah yekarah hi mipninim if
the Torah is dearer than pearls—מכהן גדול הנכנס לפני ולפנים. m'kohen gadol
hanichnas lifnai v'lifnim.
The כהן גדול kohen gadol who goes into the innermost chambers. That
is a דרשה drasha. that says even a ממזר תלמיד חכם mamzer
talmid chacham comes before a כהן גדול עם הארץ. kohen gadol am
ha'aretz. So the idea of a כהן גדול kohen gadol or whatever,
so תוספות, Tosafot, that's a hierarchy of status, as opposed to a
hierarchy of Torah, of Torah knowledge. Okay. But that is not—so תוספות
Tosafot connects this idea to the גוי goy learning Torah and about
a hierarchy of learning Torah. But that's not פשט pshat in this
גמרא. gemara More significantly, though, about this whole thing, is that there's
a great article I read about this that came out in the
volume הקדמות Akdamot about ten years ago by a Yonatan Feintuch, specifically
on this דף daf of the גמרא. gemara Anyway, he points out
that what the בבלי Bavli has done is the בבלי, Bavli, while
quoting obviously this problematic law of this difference between Jew and non-Jew
with the goring ox, is consistently nuancing it and problematizing it. And
the first thing that it did was, number one, say, hey, there
might be different reads of the פסוקים. Okay, that was not so
big because it was still having this basic הלכה. halacha. But then
right after saying the non-Jews don't keep שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva
mitzvot bnei Noach, we can take advantage of them when their ox
gores, we're having a statement of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that is
saying, you know, אשר יעשה אותם האדם, asher ya'aseh otam ha'adam, כהנים
לויים וישראלים לא נאמר אלא אדם, kohanim leviyim v'yisraelim lo ne'emar ela
adam, right, that gives a basic sort of universalist approach,
an anti-hierarchical approach like the chosenness בני ישראל bnei Yisrael approach. Any
human being who does Torah is rewarded. get to the same level
as the most chosen, as the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and so
on, right, and that is coming juxtaposed to all these not only
negative הלכות halakhot but they're not keeping the שבע מצוות sheva mitzvot
and so on. So it automatically says, you know, it's not so
black and white, they're not all רשעים, rasha'im, okay, you know, and
there's some that actually do it and actually they can reach a
very high level and so on and whatever. So it's like immediately
problematizing, you know, it's not completely embracing a rah-rah רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir type of an approach because it says מאינו מצווה ועושה me'eino
metzuveh ve'oseh etc., but it's also saying that, you know, it's not
so black and white the way we look at the other, okay.
So it's very powerful the way and it's going to continue to
problematize our, meaning problematize in a good way, you know, the attitude
towards non-Jews.
Okay, so according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir then if we damage
their ox, if they damage...
Again, I don't know, he's not making a statement about נזק, about
civil law, but it's putting a very different way of looking at
the non-Jew. Okay, now by the way,
this passage in the, in the, it appears in the ספרא, Sifra,
and it's not רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there, it's a different one,
it's a רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai or whatever, anyway, but it's a
more extended passage that looks at a lot of פסוקים that say
אדם, Adam, you know, or to, here's another one by the way,
or not אדם, Adam, but it uses a more generic word. It
says, something like פתחו שערים ויבא גוי צדיק, pitchu shearim veyavo goy
tzaddik, comes the righteous nation, and he says, ישראלים כהנים ולוים כהנים
לוים
וישראלים לא נאמר אלא גוי צדיק אפילו גוי ועוסק בתורה, Yisraelim Kohanim
uLeviyim Kohanim Leviyim veYisraelim lo ne'emar ela goy tzaddik afilu goy ve'osek
baTorah, okay, so the righteous nation which clearly in the פשט peshat
of the פסוקים is who is the righteous nation, it's ישראל. Yisrael.
He says, no, that means any גוי, goy, any גוי goy can
be a גוי צדיק goy tzaddik and deserving of the reward. So
it's an extended passage that talks about, that's a universalist ethos, that
talks really about like any, you know, about the level that anybody
can reach, okay? Like if you take a look at the first
wide line of תוספות, Tosafot, he says, איכא התם דהאי גוונא, ikka
hatam dehachay gavna, you know, over there in the ספרא, Sifra, there's
an extended passage like this, דתני התם והיינו אומר פתחו שערים ויבא
גוי צדיק ויבא כהנים ולוים וישראלים לא נאמר אלא גוי צדיק וכן
הוא אומר הטיבה ה׳ לטובים, de'tani hatam vehi'nu omer pitchu shearim veyavo
goy tzaddik veyavo Kohanim uLeviyim veYisraelim lo ne'emar ela goy tzaddik vechen
hu omer hetiva Hashem latovim, God does good to those who are
good, כהנים ולוים וישראלים לא נאמר אלא לטובים אפילו נכרי ועוסק בתורה
הרי הוא ככהן גדול. Kohanim uLeviyim uYisraelim lo ne'emar ela latovim afilu
nochri ve'osek baTorah harei hu keKohen Gadol. Okay, so it's a very
extended passage about looking at all these פסוקים that say, you know,
not so particularistic. So it's a really fascinating, a very different approach
than we normally get and here it's being juxtaposed. Of course תוספות
Tosafot is discussing it because תוספות Tosafot is bringing in other גמרות
gemarot that are very problematic, other גמרות gemarot that say the word
אדם Adam is meant to exclude a non-Jew. Right, that's very problematic
just the hermeneutics, who cares what the הלכה halakha is, the hermeneutics
that you're saying אדם Adam means to exclude a non-Jew is like
the, the exact opposite of the thrust of this passage, and תוספות
Tosafot discusses that.
Okay, even a human being what?
Right, that to some degree they're not even fully human, right. So
all right, you can read תוספות, Tosafot, you'll see his answers, okay,
and it could be a debate of תנאים Tana'im how to read
that word. Anyway, so what you have the here is this very
positive idea about non-Jews, with in the end we say אינו מצווה
ועושה, eino metzuveh ve'oseh, but it certainly nuances and balances what we've
been saying.
But nevertheless, if they damage us, they still have...
Right, we're not, we're not challenging the הלכה halakha necessarily, but we
are definitely complicating the picture. Now one more thing, one last thing
very quickly I just can't resist saying, is within a get completely
a different discussion of how to view contemporary non-Jewish religions. Do you
view them as עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei avodah zarah or not? Right,
the non-Jewish faiths. Right, so it's a whole question about how to
view that, and you know, there's a principle, and specifically Christianity and
the fact that they have the idea of the incarnation and Trinity
and that would sort of not be a, you know, consistent with
a Jewish monotheistic idea. Do, are they considered עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei
avodah zarah or not? There are some פוסקים, poskim, one or two,
it's very rare, that want to use this גמרא gemara. as a
way of being more inclusive, because they go back to the original
statement of אמר והתירן להם, amar vehitiran lahem, God released them from
the שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvot, as a way, even though the גמרא
Gemara. rejected that, you know, it says they're still punished, but as
a way of saying like, we're not going to consider what you
do anymore to be real עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So it's honest
like,
we're totally not פשט peshat of what the גמרא Gemara is saying,
but like, want to actually go back to that התיר להם, hitir
lahem, not just say they don't get reward, but they're not held
exactly as accountable as they used to be, and that can be,
give us a basis for anoth, another basis for more inclusion. All
right,
yes, but yeah, correctly, but that's specifically tying it into this דרשה.
Okay, let's go back now to the גמרא. Gemara Okay,
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. וכבר שלחה מלכות רומי שני
סרדיטות, ukevar shalkha malkhut Romi shnei sardiytot, the Roman government, the original
גרסא girsa was מלכות הרשעה, malkhut harasha, the evil government, but it
got switched to the Roman government, means the Roman government. Anyway, the
Roman government already sent two officers, now exactly what סרדיטות sardiytot are
is an interesting question, I'm sure somebody's going to tell me שטיינזלץ
Steinsaltz says, but. Lieberman points out that there actually is evidence that
the Roman government went through a process of sending out legal scholars
to different nations and to different civilizations to study their laws. And
that's he understands as the context of this story. Okay, so whether
סרדיוטות sardyotot is understood, I think it more usually means more like
officers, is how it's normally interpreted, but Lieberman understands specifically that it
means legal scholars. Okay, אתו חכמי ישראל, ayto Chachmei Yisrael, to the
sages of Israel. למדונו תורתכם, limdunu Toratechem, teach us your Torah. קרא
ושנו ושלשו, kara veshanu veshilshu, they read it two and three times,
they got it, learned it in great depth,
ושלשו, veshilshu, where are we? ושלשו. veshilshu. ובשעת פטירתן, uvish'at ptiratan, when
they went to leave, אמרו להם, amru lahem, they said to them,
דקדקנו בכל תורתכם, dikdaknu bechol Torat-chem, we have gone through your entire
תורה Torah extremely precisely, carefully. ואמת הוא, ve'emet hu, it is truth,
חוץ מדבר זה, chutz midavar zeh, with one exception, שאתם אומרים, she'atem
omrim, you say, שור של ישראל שנגח שור של נכרי פטור שור
של נכרי שנגח שור של ישראל בין תם בין מועד משלם נזק
שלם. shor shel Yisrael shenagach shor shel nochri patur shor shel nochri
shenagach shor shel Yisrael bein tam bein mu'ad meshalam nezek shalem. That
doesn't make any sense! ממה נפשך? mimah nafshach? I don't understand it,
it's not logical. אי רעהו דוקא אפילו דנכרי שנגח ישראל ליפטר. ei
re'ehu davka afilu de-nochri shenagach Yisrael lipater. אי רעהו לאו דוקא אפילו
דישראל שנגח דנכרי לחייב, ei re'ehu lav davka afilu de-Yisrael shenagach de-nochri
lechayev, then you should be chayav full in both directions. But ודבר
זה איננו מגידים אותו למלכות, vedavar zeh einu magidim oso lamalchut, we're
going to do you a favor, we're not going
to tell the government on you. Okay, now that's the end of
the story.
Now I do have to say again two quick things about this
story.
Number or a few things. Number one is, this ואי רעהו דוקא
ממה נפשך ve-ei re'ehu davka mimah nafshach is clearly a gloss into
this story. It's Aramaic, it's borrowed from the earlier גמרא. Gemara The
original text just said, you know, this one thing doesn't make sense,
שור של גוי שנגח שור של ישראל shor shel goy shenagach shor
shel Yisrael etc., ודבר זה
איננו מגידים אותו למלכות.
vedavar zeh
einu magidim
oso lamalchut.
Now if you just said that, this is the one thing that
we don't like, why don't—why do they not like it? Because it's
discriminatory, not because it's logically inconsistent. I don't get how you read
it from the פסוק, is it דוקא or לאו דוקא? No, the
problem is is that it's discriminatory, it's morally offensive. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara by inserting the Aramaic problem of ממה נפשך mimah nafshach
turned it into: you know, they just have a logical problem, they
weren't bothered at a deep level about the ethics of it. By
the way, that's also consistent with the idea of כל תורתכם אמת.
Kol Torat-chem emet. The ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's version of the story says, your
entire תורה Torah is נאה ומשובחה, na'eh umshubachah, is praiseworthy. And this
thing isn't praiseworthy, like this thing is offensive. The גמרא Gemara frames
it as, it's all true, this thing is illogical. So it downplays
the problematics, right, of this thing by making it just a logical
problem and not a moral problem. Alright, so it's interesting as well,
and there's other differences between our version and the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. One
thing is the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that they pretended to be Jews.
They presented themselves as Jews. Our גמרא Gemara doesn't, and that's very
consistent with the immediate previous statement of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which
is not the sense of this like protectiveness... control...
I'm grasping at a word here. But anyway, the sense of keeping
the תורה Torah to ourselves, right? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
the תורה Torah, is open to all. So people could come and
tell us that they're from Rome and we'll teach them תורה, Torah,
right? But the ירושלמי Yerushalmi sort of said no, no, no, they
had to present themselves as if they were Jews. And the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi also says that on their way back to Rome, they were...
God made them forget everything. So that they really couldn't report anything
or maybe they were punished or whatever it is. Again, the גמרא
Gemara here is less critical of them, you know? What they said
made sense and they were nice, they said they wouldn't tell מלכות.
malchut. So anyway, it's again, it's interesting some differences between this version
and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi version.
Yeah. ירושלמי Yerushalmi say they have to make themselves into or pretend
to be Jews and then teach them תורה, Torah so what do
you do with רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's statement that a נכרי עוסק
בתורה...? nochri osek ba-Torah...?
Well, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi doesn't have רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's statement. Again,
that's why our גמרא'ס Gemara's problematized things in a way that the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi has not.
But the בבלי Bavli also has things
that he can't.
Alright, but this גמרא Gemara has not... this גמרא Gemara is trying
to counterbalance some of the negative aspects of the prior thing. All
right, yes.
It's one of the—it's a pretty weak, you know, subversion of the
story because like really this is the only logical...?
I understand. Anyway, one last thing is that the מהרש"א, Maharsha, the
ים של שלמה Yam Shel Shlomo says, I don't understand he says,
why don't they just lie to them? Why do they have to
teach them this הלכה, halachah, right, especially it was an oral תורה
Torah at that time, they could have said oh look, the גמרא
says... so the מהרש"א Maharsha and he says aren't they afraid that
it's going to that it would lead to some type of reprisal
from the Roman government? So the מהרש"א Maharsha says from here we
see that it is forbidden to misrepresent תורה even if it was
to lead to פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. So now it doesn't mean
you have to tell them everything, it doesn't really fully explain it.
Don't teach them anything, don't misrepresent. Anyway, but that's an interesting
discussion. But that's the question, do they just sit in the ישיבה
*Yeshiva*, do they have special classes? All right, so the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this. Okay. רב שמואל בר יהודה *Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda*,
another great story here that again complicates the picture in a positive
way about non-Jews. רב שמואל בר יהודה שכיבא ליה ברתא *Rav Shmuel
bar Yehuda shchiva leh barta*. רב שמואל בר יהודה *Rav Shmuel bar
Yehuda* his daughter died. אמרי ליה רבנן לעולא *Amre leh Rabbanan l'Ulla*,
so the rabbis said to עולא *Ulla*, קום ניזיל ננחמיה *kum neizil
nenachameh*. Let's go and give him תנחומים *Tanchumim*, let's go and pay
a שבעה *shiva* call. אמר להו *Amar lehu*, he said to these,
you know, the colleagues at the ישיבה *Yeshiva*, מאי לי גבי ניחומא
דבבלאי *mai li gabei nichuma d'Bavla'ei*? Why, I don't want to participate
with your שבעה *shiva* call, with your ניחום אבלים *nichum aveilim*. I
don't like the way the Babylonians do ניחום אבלים *nichum aveilim*. עולא
*Ulla* was ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. דגידופא הוא *d'gidufa hu*. When they
do ניחום אבלים *nichum aveilim*, it winds up being a form of
blasphemy. Why? דאמרי *de-amri*, because what do they say to the person
sitting שבעה *shiva*? They say to him, מאי אפשר למעבד *mai efshar
l'me'evad*? Look, what could have been done? There was nothing that could
have been done. You know. Why is that blasphemy? Because it suggests
האי אפשר למעבד עבדי *hai efshar l'me'evad avdi*. If something could have
been done, then you would have, you're not fully accepting God's fate,
God's decree. Which is funny. If you say like there's nothing that
could have been done, that sounds like a very much accept God's
decree. But says like you couldn't have done anything. But if you
could have done anything, you would have tried to subvert God's decree.
So he has a very harsh, you know, he has—what? I understand.
עולא *Ulla* has a very sort of harsh view on things, already
theologically harsh. Let's keep on reading. Okay. אזל הוא לחודאיה *Azal hu
lachodei*. He went by himself גבי *gabei*. אמר ליה *Amar leh*. עולא
*Ulla* went and he said to him. ויאמר ה' *Vayomer Hashem*. God
said אלי *elai* to משה *Moshe*. אל תצר את מואב ואל תתגר
בם מלחמה Al tatzar et Moav ve'al titgar bam milchama. *Al tatzar
et Moav v'al titgar bam milchama*. Do not, you know, conflict מואב
Moav, *Moav* and do not wage war. וכי מה על דעתו של
משה לעשות מלחמה שלא ברשות *V'chi mah al da'ato shel Moshe l'asot
milchama shelo birshut*? What, משה *Moshe* stam on his own was going
to wage war? אלא נשא משה קל וחומר בעצמו *Ella nasa Moshe
kal vachomer be'atzmo*. Yeah, he made a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. He
said the following: ומה מדינים שלא באו לעזור למואב *u'ma Midyanim shelo
ba'u l'azor l'Moav*—the מדינים *Midyanim* that came to help מואב Moav *Moav*,
right? Remember מואב Moav *Moav* hired בלעם *Balaam*, there we go, it's
this week's, is this week's פרשה *Parsha*? No, coming up soon. קרח
*Korach*, right. חזק ואמץ
*Chazak va'ematz*. We got two to go. Okay. I knew it was
one of those names. Okay, anyway. So they went to hire בלעם
*Balaam*, you know, and you know, מואב Moav, *Moav* sort of was
the whole instigator of the whole thing and the מדינים *Midyanim* just
came to assist. צרור את המדינים והכיתם אותם *Tzor et haMidyanim v'hikitem
otam*.
Go ahead and fight against the מדינים *Midyanim*. מואבים עצמם לא כל
שכן *Moavim atzmam lo kol sheken*? Of course we should wage war
against the מואבים *Moavites*, they were the ones that started this whole
thing. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar leh Hakadosh Baruch Hu*—so God
said, don't fight against מואב *Moav*. And here's what we're getting to.
לא כשעלתה דעתך על דעתי *Lo k'sh'alta datcha al datchi*. Not like
you think is the way I think. שתי פרידות טובות יש לי
להוציא מהם *Shtei preidot tovot yesh li l'hotzi mehem*. I have two
beautiful doves to take out of them, out of עמון Amon *Ammon*
and מואב *Moav*. רות Ruth המואביה *Rut haMoavia*, Ruth the Moabite, ונעמה
העמונית *v'Naama haAmmonia*, Naamah the Ammonite, who was a wife of שלמה
Shlomo. *Shlomo*, the mother of... of... רחבעם Rechavam, *Rechavam*. And therefore, do
not, do not wage war against them. Yes, they were wicked, but
something good will come out of it. And so how's this relevant
to ניחום אבלים *nichum aveilim*? והלא שם קל וחומר *v'halo sham kal
vachomer*—look, buddy, you can make, father sitting שבעה *shiva*, you can make
a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. ומה בשביל שתי פרידות טובות חס ליה
הקדוש ברוך הוא על שתי אומות גדולות *U'ma bishvil shtei preidot tovot
chas leh Hakadosh Baruch Hu al shtei umot gedolot*—for two little doves,
for two little, you know, descendants, God had compassion over these large
nations, even though מואב *Moav* was wicked, ולא החריבם *v'lo hechrivam* and
didn't destroy them. בתו של רבי *Bito shel Rebbe*, your daughter, אם
כשירה היא וראויה היא לצאת ממנה דבר טוב *im keshera hi v'rauya
hi l'atzeit mimena davar tov*—if she's righteous and she's worthy for some
good progeny to descend from her,
so על אחת כמה וכמה דהוה חיה *al achat kama v'khama d'hava
chaya*—how much more so would she have lived? And therefore she died
because yeah, she deserved it, nothing good would have come out of
her anyway. Because if anything good would have come out of her,
she wouldn't have died. Accept God's decree, God knows what God is
doing. He did not take any classes in pastoral counseling, let me
just tell you that. Jenna is completely aghast, as she rightfully should
be. So anyway, this is of course, this is of course like
the worst example of ניחום *nichum*—like anybody ever saw that like YouTube
video of like how to pay a שבעה *shiva* call? This is
worse! Okay, anyway, anyway, what is it doing here? What it's doing
here is it's telling you you could have an entire nation that
you think is wicked, that actually waged war and tried to destroy
ישראל *Israel*, and they're not all bad. They would deserve to be
saved because something good would eventually come out of them, right? So
that obviously makes really complex a way of looking at non-Jews in
this negative light. Even if they completely appear wicked, there could always
be something good that can come out of it, right? So very
interesting how these positive גמרות *Gemaras* are being presented right after this
very harsh הלכה halakha, *Halacha*. Let's... A little bit of a persona
non grata in that household. Right. It's very powerful to have a
Holocaust
survivor acknowledge
that there were some Polish people that were... Excellent point. Right. Because
those Polish people were experienced as cruel. Right. Right. That's what someone
said
to me yesterday. Yeah, that the Poles, that they weren't... they weren't
all... all bad. It was the Germans. Uh-huh. But it's a very
powerful thing
to be able
to acknowledge... racist at the funeral. Right.
Right. I'm sorry, what?
That
at the funeral of... Rabbi Marc...
Yeah, apparently there were
some...
some racist disruptors... Really?
Wow, wow,
wow.
Yeah,
they
said they're going
to
shout
like Ceyo should
leave.
Right, right, right. Right. Wow. Okay, so let's read one more line.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: אין הקדוש ברוך הוא
מקפח שכר כל בריה. Ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mekappea sechar kol berya.
God does not hold back the reward that any creature deserves, even
some small good thing. אפילו שכר שיחה נאה, Afilu sechar sicha na'ah,
even just for a little nice speech. דאילו בכירה, De-ilu bechira, the
older daughter, now we're going to the mothers of עמון Amon, and
מואב, right? The daughters of לוט. Lot. דאילו בכירה, De-ilu bechira, the
older daughter, דקאמרה מואב. dekamera Moav. So מואב is more explicit, מאב,
Me-av, to say it's from the father, right, because she had sex
with her father. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה: Amar lei Hakadosh
Baruch Hu l'Moshe: אל תצר את מואב ואל תתגר בם מלחמה. Do
not afflict מואב and do not wage war. מלחמה הוא דלא, Milchama
hu de-lo, you can't wage war. הא אנגריא עביד בהו, Ha angarya
avid behu, you can impose on them a, like, a tax, like
you can make them, you know, subject a... what's it called? Not
a levy. What would they do to these subject nations? They'd make
them pay a tribute.
Okay. צעירה Tzi'ira דקאמרה בן עמי, dekamera Ben Ammi, but the younger
daughter who said "the son of my nation", which was less explicit,
so she was a little bit... she was more צנוע. tzanua. אמר
ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, Amar lei Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe, so
God told Moses: אל תצורם ואל תתגר בם כלל. Al tzuraim ve'al
titgar bam klal.
Do not wage... do not sort of, you know, engage them at
all. Not just do not wage war against them, don't have any
type of conflict with them. דאפילו אנגריא לא תעבוד בהו. D'afilu angarya
lo ta'avod behu. Don't even make them pay a tribute. So again,
what's also here positive about non-Jews, besides that God rewards people, is
that the acts of בנות לוט, Bnot Lot, in other מדרשים, midrashim,
is used as evidence with how licentious the non-Jews are. Look at
how licentious they are, look at this incest, look at all of
this. Here, it's being framed as: look at this great מצווה mitzvah
that, or well, we're not yet up to that they did a
מצווה, mitzvah, but look at how צנוע tzanua at least the younger
daughter was. ואמר, Ve'amar, and now we're going to get to the
fact about that they were... that it was a מצווה, mitzvah, it
wasn't licentiousness. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה:
D'amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha: לעולם יקדים
אדם לדבר מצווה. Le'olam yaktim adam l'dvar mitzvah. A person should always
run to do a מצווה. mitzvah. שבשביל לילה אחת שקדמתה בכירה לצעירה,
She-bishvil laila achat she-kadmasa bechira l'tzi'ira,
although the בכירה bechira was a little bit less careful with her
language, but she was the one that jumped forth and she was
the one that slept with her father first. And because of that
one night that she beat her younger sister to the מצווה, mitzvah,
קדמתה ארבע דורות בישראל. kadmasa arba doros b'Yisrael.
Her progeny got into the Jewish people four generations earlier. Why? Because
רות married בועז, Boaz, right? And then you have four generations: עובד,
Oved, ישי, Yishai, דוד, David, and שלמה. Shlomo. And נעמה העמונית Na'amah
ha'Ammonit married שלמה. Shlomo So the Ammonites came four generations... and both
of them married into the, you know, sort of royal family, but
the one came four generations later. ואילו צעירה עד רחבעם, Ve'ilu tzi'ira
ad Rechavam, and the younger one, עמון, Amon right, the mother of
the Ammonites, so her daughter was the mother, I mean her descendant
was the mother of רחבעם, שלמה's wife. דכתיב ושם אמו נעמה העמונית.
De-chtiv v'shem imo Na'amah ha'Ammonit. Okay. So anyway, so again, right after
this very harsh... we're not changing the הלכה, but we have really
complicated things. We've had רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir statement about אפילו גוי
שעסק בתורה הרי הוא ככהן גדול. afilu goy she'asak baTorah harei hu
k'kohen gadol. He's called אדם, Adam, אלו כהנים לויים וישראלים לא נאמר,
Elu kohanim Leviyim v'Yisraelim lo ne'emar, and so on. You know, even
these little descendants here, even something that looks completely wicked, you know,
there could be positive descendants. And then taking the story of the
mothers of... you know, about the progenitors of עמון and מואב, that
other מדרשים midrashim bring as evidence about how licentious, you know, the
non-Jews are, as evidence about these tremendous מצוות mitzvot and why they
merited, and the modesty and so on. So it's really very interesting
the way the בבלי Bavli sort of complicates the picture in a
good way, you know, from this very challenging גמרא that we just
read. Okay.
Told you it was a good גמרא today.